גוט וואך *Gutte voch*, today's דף daf *daf* is on thirty-nine, pick
up on the משנה mishna. *Mishna* on the very last line of
thirty-eight. So we've been learning a
lot about יולדת *yoledet*, that was the entire third פרק perek? *perek*.
The fourth פרק *perek* בנות כותים *Bnos Kusim* if you remember started
by women that had different statuses,
צדוקים *Tzadukim*, כותים *Kutim*, and then special cases about a question like
a woman in her that I'm trying to remember the case
anyway. It had all these special cases. Anyway the reason I'm pointing
this out is I couldn't quite figure out the order of the
משנה mishna *Mishna* here because this last משנה mishna. *Mishna* seems to
fit way back in the second פרק *perek*. Right, there was דם
עובדת כוכבים *Dam Ovedet Kochavim* and דם היולדת שלא טבלה *Dam HaYoledet
Shelo Tavla*, a woman that was a יולדת *yoledet* in גמר מצוה
*gmar mitzvah*, what's the status of the blood? So all these interesting
cases. And then we doubled back to יולדת *yoledet* and we talked
about דם קושי *Dam Koshi*. And now we're going to see as
you see basically a standard question that gets us back to basic
הלכות halachos נדה nida *Hilchos Nidda*. So again, you could try your
best to figure out the theory of organization here. I did see
some that wanted to say that this פרק *perek* was focused on
דם זיבה zivah *Dam Ziva* because to some degree everything deals with
also the case of a זב zav *zav*, but I think it's
a bit of a stretch. Whatever it is, this next משנה mishna.
*Mishna* gets us into basic issues relating to הלכות נדה nida, *Hilchos
Nidda* and away from the discussion about יולדת *yoledet* and דם קושי
*Dam Koshi* and so on. So let's take a look. משנה mishna.
*Mishna*. כל אחת עשר יום בחזקת טהרה b'chezkat tahara? *Kol achas asar
yom bechezkas tahara*. For the entire eleven days, what eleven days is
it? The eleven days after נדה niddah *Nidda* that a woman is
if she bleeds will be a זבה zava, *zava*. And the logic
of those eleven days is that the likelihood a woman will bleed
is not considered a normal menstruation for a woman to bleed between
day eight and eighteen after the previous menstruation. It's basically an assumption
that the minimal menstrual period is nineteen days, eighteen days, so the
next logical thing would be day nineteen. Anything less than that makes
her a זבה zava. *zava*. So because days eight through eighteen are
considered unusual or unnatural or non-standard and not menstrual blood, she's also
assumed to be טהורה tehora. *tehora*. She doesn't have to check during
those days because she can assume she's not bleeding, those are the
days she's not supposed to be bleeding. Now what does it exactly
mean that she can assume she's טהורה tehora. *tehora*? We will discuss
in the גמרא gemara *Gemara* because you might remember that if it's
about טהרות taharos. *Taharos*, we had a משנה mishna. *Mishna* that basically
said every single woman under the sun has to check for טהרות
*Taharos* at every time during the year except maybe when she's נדה
niddah, *Nidda* when it's irrelevant, right you might remember that משנה mishna
*Mishna* way back on דף יב *Daf Yud Beis* or something. So
even if she's not expecting, why is she any worse than a
מעוברת *muberet*, זקנה *zekeina*, those also are מסולקות דמים misulakot damim, *mesulakos
damim* and they still have to check. So we'll talk about that.
But the משנה mishna, *Mishna* does say those eleven days בחזקת טהרה
b'chezkat tahara? *bechezkas tahara*. She can assume she's not bleeding. Top of
לט עמוד א *Lamed Tes Amud Aleph*. ישבה לה ולא בדקה *Yashva
lo velo badka*. Now
let's say, and this is not necessarily this woman, but any woman
didn't check when she was supposed to check. And this might be
referring to the twice daily check that in a world of טהרות
*Taharos* women are supposed to do. שוגגת *Shogega*, אונס *ones*, הזידה *hizida*,
it doesn't matter why she didn't check, whether she was negligent, whether
it was out of her control, whether she was intentional, ולא בדקה
*velo badka*.
She didn't check when she was supposed to check, any woman. טהורה
tehorah *Tehora*.
Nevertheless she's טהורה tehorah. *tehora*. Okay? So any woman basically, even though
women have to check twice a day in that world, they are
if they don't do what they're supposed to do, they're טהורה tehorah
*tehora*. הגיע זמן וסתה ולא בדקה *Higia zman vesta velo badka*. Now
what happens if the day of their expected period arrives and they
didn't check? That's a little different. That day they are assumed to
be getting their period unless they can prove otherwise. So that's not
just an obligation to check, that really raises questions about what her
status is. So if the time of her period arrives and she
didn't check, הרי זו טמאה temeiah. *harei zu tmeia*, then she has
to assume that she is טמאה temeiah *tmeia*. And this משנה Mishnah
*Mishna* is the basic foundation for our practice today that women check
at the day that they're expected to get their period. And because
the two checks a day every single day, that's for a world
of טומאה tumah וטהרה *tuma ve-tahara*. That's just an obligation of checking,
it doesn't have consequences of assuming you're טמאה temeiah. *tmeia* or טהורה
tehorah, *tehora* as we see here, even if you didn't do it
you're טהורה tehorah, *tehora*. And that's just for world of טומאה וטהרה
*tuma ve-tahara*. But the day of your וסת veset, *veset*, the time
of your וסת veset, *veset* when you're expecting your period, there we
assume you're going to get your period unless you can prove otherwise.
So there if you don't check you are assumed to be טמאה
temeiah. *tmeia* and that checking therefore we still do today. So this
is extremely important for today's practice. רבי מאיר אומר Rabbi Meir omer,
*Rabbi Meir omer*, Rabbi Meir says, אם הייתה במחבוא *im haysa bemachvo*,
she was in hiding, והגיע זמן וסתה ולא בדקה *vehigia zman vesta
velo badka*, the time of her וסת veset? *veset* arrived and she
didn't check, הרי זו טהורה tehorah. *harei zu tehora*. In that situation
where she's in like afraid for her life and she's in hiding
from the oppressors,
then she's considered not to be, even if she doesn't check we
don't assume she bled. Why? מפני שהחרדה מסלקת את הדמים *mipnei shecharada
mesalekes es hadamim*. Fear causes the bleeding to be suspended. So that
would be a special override case to the normal rule that during
her period of her וסת veset? *veset* without checking she's assumed to
be טמאה teme'ah. *tmeia*. אבל ימי הזב והזבה ושומרת יום כנגד יום
*Aval yemei hazav vehazava veshomeret yom kineged yom*.
Let's say, so now we've dealt with you're right now טהורה *tehora*,
but are you in your
eleven day period normally bleed the rest of the time or on
your שעת וסת. sha'at vestet But let's say you actually are טמא.
tamei. You became a זב zav as a man, we're introducing men
again, or a זבה, zava, or you bled once as a woman
during the eleven days and you're a זבה קטנה zava ketana שומרת
יום כנגד יום. shomeret yom k'neged yom. And now you need clean
days. You have to check the following days to make sure you're
clean. That's the obligation of a זב zav and a זבה. zava
In those cases, הרי אלו בחזקת טומאה. harei elu b'chezkat tumah. The
whole point is, because you bled three times and you're a זב
zav or זבה, zavah we're afraid you're going to continue to have
a flow. And those, if you don't check, you're assumed to have
had the flow if you don't check. And this is going to
lead into, not the requirement to check on the time of the
וסת, veset but the requirement to check when? For the שבעה נקיים,
shiva neki'im, right? After a woman finishes bleeding, she needs seven clean
days and she has to check during those seven clean days. That
is the last line of the משנה. Mishnah That during the period
when you became a זבה zavah or זב or שומרת יום shomeret
yom and you need clean days to follow, you have to be
concerned that you will be bleeding and you're בחזקה b'chezka or you're
flowing, you'll be בחזקת טומאה b'chezkat tumah and therefore the checking there
is of a different quality. Okay, so basically, there's the normal checking
which בדיעבד b'diavad if you don't do it not a problem, and
we don't even do that checking nowadays. The checking at the time
of the וסת, veset which if you don't do it you're assumed
to be טמאה. teme'ah. There was a question if you remember in
the context before the גמרא gemara. whether וסת דאורייתא, veset d'oraita, וסת
דרבנן. veset d'rabanan. But either way, we assume you're טמאה teme'ah. whether
דאורייתא d'oraita or דרבנן. d'rabanan. And that we do nowadays. A woman
checks when she's expecting her period, and if she didn't check then
she's assumed that she has bled unless she checks afterwards.
And finally, a hint towards the discussion of this issue of checking
during the שבעה נקיים. shiva neki'im. And that that also is of
a different quality. So now we have to go back to the
first line. With all this checking done all the time, what does
it mean that the eleven days
is בחזקת טהרה? be-chezkat taharah, For what purpose? Let's take a look
at the גמרא. gemara למאי הלכתא? l'mai hilchata?
For what purpose are you telling me that during those eleven days
she's בחזקת טהרה? be-chezkat taharah, אמר רב יהודה amar Rav Yehuda לומר
lomar to tell you שאינה צריכה בדיקה. she'eina tzricha bedika. She doesn't
have to check. A reasonable assumption. How does that fit into what
we taught way back in the first פרק? I don't know, we'll
talk about it in a minute. Let's see what the גמרא gemara
does with this. והא מדקתני
סיפא, v'ha midektani seifa, the end of the משנה mishnah says, ישבה
ולא בדקה, yashva v'lo badka, if a woman didn't check when she
was supposed to, she's still טהורה. מכלל דלכתחילה בעי בדיקה. miklal d'lechatchila
ba'ei bedika. It sounds like at the outset she had to check.
If בדיעבד b'diavad she didn't, she's okay, but right after saying eleven
days, it says, and if she didn't check when she was supposed
to. So presumably she was supposed to check during that time. So
the גמרא Gemara says, no. סיפא אתאן לימי נדה. seifa atan l'yemei
nida.
The סיפא, seifa, the end is talking about a different הלכה. halacha.
And here's how you read the משנה. mishnah This is a reasonable
read of the משנה. mishnah והכי קאמר. v'hachi ka'amar. כל י"א יום
בחזקת טהרה ולא בעי בדיקה. kol yud aleph yom b'chezkat tahara v'lo
ba'ei bedika. First הלכה halacha is,
during the eleven days, we'll never assume she's going to bleed and
she doesn't have to check. Number one, those eleven days, don't even
bother checking. Number one. Number two, all the other days of the
month that you are checking, even there בדיעבד b'diavad it's not מעכב.
me'akev. אבל ימי נדותה, aval yemei niduta, during the rest of the
נדה niddah. days where she could become a נדה, niddah בעי בדיקה.
ba'ei bedika. She does have to check. ישבה
ולא בדקה, yashva v'lo badka, and if she didn't check when she
was supposed to, בין באונס בין בשוגג, bein b'ones bein b'shogeg, whether
on purpose or out of her control or negligent, ולא בדקה טהורה.
v'lo badka tehora. She is טהורה.
So that is a very nice read of the משנה. mishnah Eleven
days, don't have to bother checking. All the rest of the time
when we tell you you have to check twice a day, even
there it's not מעכב, me'akev, it doesn't become a problem if you
didn't do it post-facto. Now, the only, that's a very nice read
of the משנה. mishnah. The only problem is, what about the משנה
mishnah before that said כל הנשים, kol hanashim, you know, even המסולקות
דמים hamisulakot damim need to check twice? So there's a long
תוספות tosafot that deals with it, and he basically says, you know,
we'll have to come up with a somewhat
counter-intuitive conclusion and say the following. If a woman is pregnant or
pre-menopausal or after childbirth, even though they're מסולקות דמים, misulakot damim that
is a stint that is going to be that is temporary and
is going to be passing. And therefore we require them to check
even though they're מסולקות דמים because it's a temporary state and in
general they have to check
on a regular basis. But the eleven days, day eight to eighteen,
is never a period where they will ever have to where we
should ever be concerned that they might bleed. And therefore, yes, there
is that somewhat counter-intuitive conclusion that on a regular monthly basis, day
eight to eighteen, they're off the hook because that's never a time
we're concerned about. Whereas if they're pregnant or pre-menopausal or whatever, even
though we know they're not going to bleed, since it's during normal
periods they have to check. Obviously, I intentionally left out one of
that group of four. I said pre-menopausal, pregnant, and nursing.
Which one didn't I say, do you remember?
You can figure it out. Pre-menopausal, pregnant, nursing.
Post-menopausal. So post-menopausal, she's never going to go back to having regular
bleeding. So תוספות tosafot tries to deal with it. Anyway, it's a
very interesting and very reasonable read of the משנה, mishnah? but a
very serious question about how you fit. to the idea that we
until that we've assumed that every single woman every single
day basically has to check in a time of טומאה and טהרה.
taharah. Now we go on. רב חסדא אמר רב חסדא לא צריכה
אלא Rav Hisda amar Rav Hisda lo tzricha ela לרבי מאיר. le-Rabbi
Meir.
This idea that she's בחזקת טהרה, she doesn't have to check. So
what's its purpose? Its purpose is for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir דאמר
de-amar אשה שאין לה וסת אסורה לשמש. ishah she-ein lah veset asurah
le-shamesh.
Remember רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said that if a woman does not
have a fixed time of seeing then she can never see she
can't stay with her husband and can't have sex because any day
might be the day she's going to get her period and therefore
you're never allowed you can't stay you know
that woman can't stay married. הני מילי בימי נדתה. Hani milei bimei
niddatah. So actually she's not really forbidden to have sex all the
time. She's only forbidden to have sex during the נדה niddah time.
אבל בימי זיבתה בחזקת טהרה קיימא. Aval bimei zivatah be-chezkat taharah kaima.
But during but between days eight and eighteen she's okay. So basically
a woman until she gets her period she can't have sex with
her husband. But once she has her period and then waits seven
days then she can have sex with her husband for the next
eleven days, from day eight to eighteen, because those are always considered
day eight to eighteen from the last time she bled are always
assumed to be
you're not going to get your next period during this time. Makes
an immense amount of sense. Even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that's concerned
you might get your period whenever, but for it to be the
next period there needs to be some minimal spacing between the previous
one. So day eight to eighteen you're safe. Very nice limit on
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. But now the גמרא Gemara has a question.
אי הכי אמאי אמר רבי
מאיר יוציא ולא יחזיר? Ei hachi amai amar Rabbi Meir yotzi ve-lo
yachzir?
So why did רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say that a husband has
to divorce his wife and not remarry her ever if he's if
she has a fluctuating וסת? veset. Why
not? Why can't he stay married to her and regularly have sex
between days eight and eighteen? So the גמרא Gemara says דילמא אתי
לאקולי בימי נדה. Dilma atei le-akulei bimei niddah. No,
because it's a dangerous situation. Since every month he's only going to
have this limited time to have sex, we're afraid the יצר הרע
yetzer hara will get the better of him and he'll wind up
having sex you know once he had sex on day eighteen, have
sex on day nineteen, have sex on day twenty, come on, she's
not a נדה, Niddah, she hasn't bled, you know who cares if
she doesn't have a fixed וסת? veset
So therefore because we basically can't trust them to limit it to
days eight to eighteen we have to say get divorced. Not very
nice with this woman that now has no you know no recourse
or nothing to do, but anyway that is how we answer. But
at least so תוספות Tosafot says to what purpose does it say
they can have sex if he has to make them get divorced?
תוספות Tosafot says
okay it's before they got around to getting divorced they're still allowed
to have sex during that time. Okay all right now the גמרא
Gemara goes on. All right now moving on.
Okay so that's answer number one is don't bother checking. Don't need
to check, which
is strange because until now we thought you always have to check.
Number two is for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir at least you don't
have to be concerned she might bleed and you're even if you
have to check or whatever and you're allowed to have sex between
days eight and eighteen. And now the גמרא Gemara just finishes up
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the גמרא Gemara says like this. דילמא
אתי לאקולי בימי נדה, Dilma atei le-akulei bimei niddah,
right, maybe he'll come to you know to
actually go overboard and
and transgress and have sex during the time of נדה. niddah Not
when she is a נדה niddah but when she could become a
נדה niddah after day eighteen. So the גמרא Gemara says הכי קתני
סיפא Hachi katani seifa
but it says at the end הגיע שעת וסתה ולא בדקה, Higi'a
she'at vestah ve-lo badkah, that when the time of the וסת veset.
came and she didn't check, מכלל דבאשה שיש לה וסת עסקינן. Miklal
de-be-ishah she-yesh lah veset askinan.
So it sounds right it says since it seems like the next
line connects to the first line, it says the entire eleven days
she's בחזקת טהרה, when the time of her וסת veset came here's
the consequence. So it sounds like we're talking about a woman that
has a וסת. veset. It says what do you do when the
time of her וסת veset. comes and you're telling me the only
relevance of the first line is a woman without a fixed וסת.
veset, So the גמרא Gemara says חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. Hasorei michasra
ve-hachi katani. No, it's missing some words. You have to understand. Talking
about different cases. Here's here's how to understand. כל י"א יום בחזקת
טהרה ושריא לבעלה. Kol yod-alef yom be-chezkat taharah u-shraya le-ba'alah.
For the first eleven for day eight to eighteen she is assumed
טהורה even if she doesn't have a וסת veset, and she's permitted
to her husband. We don't have to be concerned during those days.
ובימי נדה אסורה, U-vimei niddah asurah,
but during the rest of the days when it's not between day
eight and eighteen, she can't have sex with her husband. במה דברים
אמורים, Bameh devarim amurim, who who are we talking about? These are
the words we're now adding in the משנה Mishnah, implicitly, באשה שאין
לה וסת, Be-ishah she-ein lah veset, a woman without a fixed period.
That's where you have to say but eight to eighteen you're safe.
אבל יש לה וסת Aval yesh lah veset if she has a
fixed period, מותרת, mutteret, she can have sex whenever she wants with
her husband. I mean assuming she's טהורה. There's no limit. Have sex
anytime. However,
וצריכה בדיקה, ve-tzricha bedikah, but she still has to check on a
regular basis even if she has a period. ישבה ולא בדקה, Yashva
ve-lo badkah, if she didn't check, שוגגת אונסת מזידה, shogget oneset mezida,
whether intentionally or not intentionally, דלא בדקה טהורה, de-lo badkah tehorah, she's
then she's still טהורה if she didn't check like she was supposed
to. However, הגיע שעת וסתה ולא בדקה, higi'a she'at vestah ve-lo badkah,
once the time of her period came and she didn't check, טמאה.
temeiah, She's טמאה. temeiah So basically what it does is like a
previous answer, we're cutting off the first line from the rest of
it. The first line is eleven days are okay, meaning a woman
without a וסת. veset The rest of the משנה Mishnah is talking
about a woman with a וסת. vestet. A woman without a וסת,
vestet at least you're safe between days eight and eighteen. A woman
with a וסת, vestet, don't think it means they're off the hook.
You can have sex anytime, but they still have to check twice
a day. However, if you didn't check you're okay except for when
the וסת vestet comes, then if you didn't check we still have
a problem.
Okay, yes, so this is דף ב daf bet about this idea
of getting divorced because now we're talking about a woman who doesn't
have a וסת.
vestet Right, yeah, so it's only רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says
she has to get divorced, but we're saying the משנה Mishnah is
going according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and telling you even though
normally we demand divorce, if they didn't get divorced or whatever, they
didn't get around to it yet, between day 8 and 18 you're
still okay.
And didn't we say some time ago that having a fixed וסת
vestet is unusual actually?
For us nowadays. The גמרא Gemara assumes it's standard. Nowadays, most women,
it might have something to do with, I mean what we'll get
to when we discuss how to determine a וסת, vestet, about how
וסתות vestos are taught and about how much we're in touch with
our bodies and so on. But the גמרא Gemara assumes that וסת
vestet. is very, very much the standard.
Okay, anyway, the סיפא seifa says like this: והא מדקתני סיפא, Ve-ha
mid-katani seifa, but one minute, the end of the משנה says, one
moment where am I, והא מדקתני סיפא רבי מאיר, Ve-ha mid-katani seifa
Rabbi Meir, but the end of the משנה says that רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says if you're in hiding, you don't have to worry
about שעת וסת vestet, because the fear causes suspension of bleeding. So
if the end of the משנה is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רישא
לאו רבי מאיר, reisha lav Rabbi Meir, the beginning is not רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So right? Because presumably now it's a new opinion.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is now introduced at the end. So it
says, no, כולה רבי מאיר היא, kula Rabbi Meir hi, no, it's
all רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. והכי קאמר, ve-hachi ka'amar, this is what
it means: אם לא היתה במחבוא והגיעה שעת וסתה ולא בדקה טמאה,
im lo hayta be-machavo ve-higi'ah sha'at vestah ve-lo badka teme'ah,
if she was not in hiding and the time of a וסת
veses, came and she didn't check she's טמאה. temeiah. רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir. אומר, and this is just within the, because this is רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says: אם היתה במחבוא והגיעה
שעת וסתה ולא בדקה טהורה, im hayta be-machavo ve-higi'ah sha'at vestah ve-lo
badka tehorah, if she was in hiding and the time came and
she didn't check then she's טהורה, she doesn't have to
worry, שחרדה מסלקת את הדמים, she-charadah mesalekat et ha-damim, the fear causes
it to be suspended. You see this גמרא Gemara is very easy
because 80 percent of it is repeatedly quoting the משנה. Anyway, but
that's, you know, not so bad. Yes, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. comes
at the end, but he doesn't necessarily argue on the beginning. He's
qualifying the beginning. When are we concerned after the time of the
וסת veses. passed? We're concerned in a normal case, but if she's
hiding and there's fear, we're not concerned after the time passes. So
the whole משנה is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir The first line is
a woman without a וסת, veses the rest of it is a
woman with a וסת. veses So right now what are the answers
we have for the משנה? Answer number one is during those 11
days a woman doesn't have to check, which is a huge shock
because תוספות Tosafot tries to explain why that's true. Normally every woman
has to check twice if it's טהרות. And answer number two is
that we are dealing with רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir. and saying that
for a woman without a וסת, veses, that's the first line, she
still doesn't have to be concerned about having sex between 8 and
18. Now we're going to try answer number three. רבא אמר, Rava
amar, רבא Rava says here's the relevance of those 11 days: לומר
שאינה מטמאה מעת לעת. lomar she-einah metame'ah me-et le-et. Ah, you thought
we had gotten out of that. So from the very first דף
of נדה, niddah when a woman bleeds, how much backwards does she
have to be concerned that she might have begun bleeding? 24 hours
back you assume that she's טמאה. Let's say, however, she bleeds during
a period of מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim. Remember one of the relevances
of מסולקת דמים, mesuleket damim, or the relevance,
is not that she doesn't have to check—we just said that pretty
much a woman has to check all the time—but that when she
bleeds, she doesn't have to be חושש choshesh 24 hours back. Because
she's מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim and we assume it just happened right
now. Okay, so that's what he said. That's the relevance of the
11 days. Maybe it's true she does have to check during those
11 days just like the pregnant woman, but when she bleeds, she
doesn't have to be worried 24 hours back because that is a
similar period of מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim. That's a very nice answer
because that's how we know מסולקת דמים mesuleket damim has functioned until
now, that you don't have to worry 24 hours
back. מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask you on this: here we have a
ברייתא, braita, הנדה והזבה והשומרת יום כנגד יום והיולדת, Ha-niddah ve-ha-zavah ve-ha-shomeret
yom keneged yom ve-ha-yoledet, a woman who is נדה niddah or זבה
zavah and this doesn't mean נדה niddah, or זבה zavah period, it
means actually she is a נדה niddah, or she is a זבה
zavah and she's counting her seven days. Actually the נדה niddah, period
let me just don't check רש"י, Rashi,
one minute,
no, I'm sorry, so the נדה niddah, means when she first becomes
a נדה, niddah, but זבה zavah, the way רש"י Rashi at least
is reading this—I assume you could read it otherwise—but רש"י Rashi is
reading it, so whether a woman has her first bleeding and she
became a נדה, niddah, or she's a זבה zavah and she's trying
to get her clean days, והשומרת יום כנגד יום, ve-ha-shomeret yom keneged
yom, or she became a זבה קטנה zavah ketanah and trying to
get one clean day, one minute,
no, no, no, hold on, hold on, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I
did it, I misread it again. Okay, let's try, start again. מיתיבי,
Meitivei, okay. הנדה, Ha-niddah, a woman bleeds once and she became a
נדה, niddah או הזבה, o ha-zavah, a woman is bleeding during the
11 days and becoming a זבה, zavah and she bled three times,
והשומרת יום כנגד יום, ve-ha-shomeret yom keneged yom, or she's bleeding during
the 11 days and became a זבה קטנה, zavah ketanah, she bled
once. So a woman bled sometime during the month. Either she made
herself into a נדה, niddah or she made herself a זבה קטנה
zavah ketanah or a זבה גדולה, zavah gedolah, but she had that
bleeding that made her טמאה. והיולדת, Ve-ha-yoledet, or a woman during childbirth
where maybe she's bleeding because of the process of childbirth. כולם מטמאות
מעת לעת. kulam metame'ot me-et le-et.
So you all חושש choshesh 24 hours back. So here you see
that it says that whenever a woman bleeds, whether even in the
זבה zava period, she has to be concerned 24 hours back. So
תיובתא. tiyuvta. So גמרא Gemara says, okay, that's it, forget that answer.
Such a gorgeous answer, it was exactly what we know מסולקת דמים
mesuleket damim is, but here it says a woman who is a
זבה zava, has to be חושש choshesh 24 hours back. Now the
reason I was misreading it is because when I, because I was
actually thinking when I learned this that there's an answer to this.
You could have said a זבה zava doesn't mean when she becomes
a זבה, zava but a זבה zava, could mean when she is
a זבה zava and trying to get her seven clean days, that
then she's חושש choshesh 24 hours back. But the גמרא Gemara chooses
not to read it that way and maybe that would have also
raised similar questions, but anyway and therefore the גמרא Gemara, says, although
that makes a lot of sense, no, when a woman bleeds during
the 11 days and she becomes a זבה, zava she is חוששת
chosheshes 24 hours back. So by the way, here's where תוספות Tosafos
puts together at the end and emphasizes, underscores the irony of the
first statement he said. Now we are saying that this woman when
she bleeds during the 11 days is חוששת chosheshes 24 hours back,
and according to the first answer of the גמרא, Gemara רב יהודה,
Rav Yehuda, even so she doesn't have to check. So it's like
during the 11 days she doesn't have to check and if she
bleeds she's חוששת chosheshes 24 hours back. The exact inverse of the
pregnant woman, right, who if she bleeds is not concerned 24 hours
back and still has to check twice a day. So that it's
really becomes a very bizarre exception to what we said before. But
the simple answer that she wouldn't have to be חוששת chosheshes would
have made it straight in line with what we knew, but the
גמרא Gemara rejects that. So we have three answers now. Number one
is she doesn't have to check. Quite bizarre, especially now that we
know that he still חוששת chosheshes 24 hours back. חוששת. chosheshes. Number
two is it's according to רבי Rebbe? מאיר. Number three is not
חוששת chosheshes 24 hours back, which would have been a perfect answer,
but does not fit with the ברייתא. braisa. Answer number four. רב
הונא בר חייא, Rav Huna bar Chiya, you know, it could have
been like a like a nice trivia like a quiz, right? Okay,
what do you think this could be? רב הונא בר חנינא אמר
שמואל, Rav Huna bar Chinena amar Shmuel, רב הונא בר חנינא סתם
אמר משמואל, Rav Huna bar Chinena stam amar mishmuel, לומר שאינה קובעת
וסת בתוך ימי זיבתה. lomar she’eina kova’as vest b’soch yemei zivasa. All
right, so you thought you were going to get off easy today.
So far it's been pretty straightforward, but he says no, no, here's
the relevant point. The point of these 11 days considered the חזקת
טהרה, chezkas tahara, meaning you basic, are basically days in which you
don't assume if she's bleeding again it's another cycle. So here actually
he says הלכה halacha that's extremely straightforward. If the reason she's a
זבה zavah between day 8 and 18 is because we assume it's
not menstrual bleeding, then what that means is a woman cannot establish
a וסת, veses a regular period in fewer than 18, than 19
days. Right, if a woman bleeds every 19 days, that's a regular
period. But let's say a woman bleeds every 18 days or every
15 days, we will refuse to recognize that as a period because
the whole
logic of
זבה zavah is to
say that between day 8 and 18 it cannot be the next
period. So therefore, when we try to establish that sense that you
have a fixed pattern of bleeding and you have a וסת קבוע
veses kavua with relevance, what is the relevance of וסת קבוע? veses
kavua? רש"י Rashi here says, let me read you one line of
רש"י Rashi because in, like רש"י, Rashi, as he brilliantly always does,
in like five words tells you the major two נפקא מינה'ס nafka
minas of having a fixed וסת. vesset So if you look at
רש"י Rashi he says, one minute, let me find the רש"י. Rashi.
Hold on. Just enough to find the רש"י. Rashi. I will tell
you if I can't find it. Anyway. Okay, so רש"י Rashi says,
you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, two lines down of the
wide lines, רש"י Rashi says, no that was רש"י Rashi from before.
All right, I'm just going to tell you. There was one רש"י
Rashi that said it beautifully in like five words and I can't
find it right
now. But the two major נפקא מינה'ס nafka minas of having a
fixed וסת vesset are the following. Number one, that even when your
וסת vesset, shifts to a different day, let's say
a woman normally sees every 30 days and in the last two
three month and the last two months she's been seeing on day
25. Nevertheless, she still has to be concerned that she might be
bleeding on day 30 because since it's a fixed וסת, vesset,
therefore it is not concerned to have shifted unless it
changes three months in a row. But any less than a
change of three months in a row, that וסת vesset, is still
fixed and she does not and she still has to be...
he says five days later she has to check again if she
hasn't bled on day 25. Now it doesn't mean she doesn't have
to worry about day 25, she also have to worry about the
most recent month, but she doesn't stop worrying about
her regular period unless it is unless it is undermined for three
months. So number one is stringency. The stringency is is that she
doesn't stop worrying about
it until after she always has to worry about it until it's
reversed three months in a row. The other הלכה halacha that of
a וסת קבוע veses kavua is that after the day passes of
her וסת קבוע, veses kavua, right, if she doesn't check she assumes
that she's טמאה, correct? Right? Remember that הלכה halacha that if she
doesn't check then she is assumed to be טמאה because that day
passed. So therefore that's another stringency that without checking she has to
assume that she is טמאה. Okay, so those are the... two major
הלכות *halachos* of a וסת קבוע vesset kavua. *veses kavua*. There's ways
that there's also leniencies and so on, but those are the two
major הלכות *halachos*. Okay, I'll give you just one obvious leniency. If
a woman doesn't have a וסת קבוע vesset kavua. *veses kavua*, Rabbi
Meir goes far as so far to say he has to get
divorced from her husband. So the positive of a וסת קבוע vest
kavua. *veses kavua* is it alleviates concerns during the rest of the
month. The negative is it heightens concerns about that day. That day
is always a day you're going to be concerned about until it's
reversed three times, and it's your concern if you didn't check that
she's טמאה *teme'ah*, but it removes concerns from the other days. But
that's the importance of having a וסת קבוע vestet kavua. *veses kavua*.
So now, the הלכה *halacha* of these 11 days are days you
normally don't get your period has a very relevant הלכה *halacha*, that
we're never going to consider something less than 19 days to be
a וסת vesset, *veses*. That's the whole point of 8 to 18
is that it's זבה zavah *zava* blood because it's not נדה niddah
*niddah* blood. So let's take a look. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
like this, אמר *amar* so let's read it again, רבא אמר *Rava
amar* רב הונא Rav Huna בר חייה אמר שמואל Shmuel, לא lo,
באתי לומר לך שאינה קובעת וסת vest בתוך ימי זיבתה *Rav Huna
bar Chiya amar Shmuel lo basi lomar lach she'eina kova'as veses besoch
yemei zivasah*. She cannot have a fixed וסת vest *veses* if it
is occurring between days 8 and 18. אמר רב יוסף *Amar Rav
Yosef*, so רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* said, who was a student of
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda *Rav Yehuda* who was a student of שמואל
*Shmuel*, right this is said in the name of שמואל *Shmuel*, okay,
so this is רב הונא *Rav Huna* in the name
of שמואל *Shmuel*, but רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* was a student
of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda *Rav Yehuda*. So he said, אמר רב
יוסף *Amar Rav Yosef*, לא שמיע לי הא שמעתתא *lo shmi'a li
ha shema'ata*. You know, I never heard that. You're telling this to
me in the name of שמואל *Shmuel*. I'm the student of רב
יהודה *Rav Yehuda* who was a תלמיד מובהק *talmid muvhak* of שמואל
*Shmuel* and I never heard it. Now if you remember or you
might know that רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* got sick and forgot his
learning. So sometimes he would say לא שמיע לי *lo shmi'a li*
like I never heard that and he's sort of questioning the veracity
of a statement because he said I would have remembered it if
you're saying it in the name of שמואל *Shmuel*. But now but
there's usually a response to that. So אמר ליה amar lei, אביי
*amar lei Abaye*, אביי *Abaye* said back who was a student of
רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*, את מר תניתה ניהלן *at mar sanisah nihan*.
No, you actually you forgot it but you told it to us.
And this הלכה *halacha* that during the ימי זיבה yimei zivah, *yemei
ziva* she does not get a regular וסת vest *veses*. והאמרת לן
*Veha'amart lan*, based on this teaching this משנה *Mishnah* you explained this
position of שמואל *Shmuel*. Here is the משנה *Mishnah*. היתה למודה להיות
רואה יום ט"ו *Haisah lemudah lihayos ro'ah yom tes-vav*. A woman regularly
and this is one of the major הלכות *halachos* of a וסת
קבוע vestet kavua, *veses kavua* like I said that you always have
to be concerned about that day until it gets reversed three times.
So a woman would normally see on day 15. ושינתה ליום כ'
vashinsah leyom chaf, *Veshinsah leyom chaf*. And now she switches and she
sees on day 20. זה וזה אסורין *Ze vaze asurin*. Don't have
sex on day 15 because that's your fixed time and and being
reversed once doesn't matter, but also if you didn't bleed on day
15, don't have sex on day 20 because you have to be
concerned about the most previous month and your fixed time. So זה
וזה אסורין בתשמיש *Ze vaze asurin bishimush*. שינתה פעמיים ליום כ' *Shinsah
pa'amayim leyom chaf*. Two months running she's now seen on day 20.
Looks like her cycle is changing. You still can't forget about day
15. It has to be three times. זה וזה אסורין *Ze vaze
asurin*. Next month you have to not have sex both on day
15, which has been your fixed pattern, and on what's seeming to
become your new pattern, day 20. You don't have to check. She
checks on 15 to have sex, right. Okay, but on the days
that you are now the days of concern, the specific days 15
and 20 you do. So always you have to be concerned with
the most recent and with the fixed if you have a fixed.
However, if it is and then but however the implicit point is
that if it's a third time, right I think the end of
the משנה *Mishnah* says explicitly, then she stops worrying about day 15
and now it shifts to day 20. Fine. Now we've got a
problem. It says that she regularly sees on day 15, which is
during the ימי זיבה yimei zivah, *yemei ziva*. והאמרת לן עלה *Veha'amart
lan alah*, and you רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* when we were learning
this משנה *Mishnah* you said to us, אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, *Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel*, you said
to us in the name of your רבי *Rebbi*, רב יהודה *Rav
Yehuda* in the name of שמואל *Shmuel*, לא שנו אלא ט"ו לטבילתה
Lo shanu ela tes-vav litvilatah, *lo shanu ela tes-vav litvilasah*. It doesn't
mean 15 from the last time she bled, which would put her
smack in the middle of ימי זיבה yimei zivah. *yemei ziva*. It
means 15 from the time she went to the מקוה mikvah, *mikvah*.
Okay, which means assuming again a woman is going to the מקוה
*mikvah* after the night of the seventh, seventh day after the onset
of bleeding. They weren't doing clean days yet for a woman who's
a נדה niddah *niddah*. So if you add right to the night
of the מקוה *mikvah* is after seven days after the onset of
bleeding. So 15 after מקוה *mikvah night is day 22. That gets
her out of the זבה zavah *zava* period. Okay, so that's how
you explained it. ט"ו לטבילתה *Tes-vav litvilasah*, day 15 from the מקוה
*mikvah*, שהן כ"ב לראייתה *shehein chaf-beis lir'iyasa*, which is 22 from the
last bleeding. דהתם בימי נדותה קיימא *Dehasam bimei niddusah kaia*, because then
she would be during the נדה niddah, *niddah* period. אבל ט"ו לראייתה
*Aval tes-vav lir'iyasa*, but 15 from the last time she saw, ימי
זיבתה קיימא *yemei zivasah kaia*, which would put her smack in the
middle of the זבה zavah *zava* period. לא קבעה *Lo kav'ah*, she
does not have a fixed וסת vest *veses*. And therefore we do
not say that after it gets reversed once, twice, or whatever you
still have to worry about it. It's not a fixed וסת vest
*veses*. Don't worry about it. אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Papa, *Amar
Rav Papa*, so that's that's an answer the גמרא *Gemara* brings to
light. And by the way, it's a very nice answer because it
directly addresses why the תורה *Torah* calls her a זבה zavah *zava*,
right? The תורה *Torah*'s calling her a זבה zavah *zava* because it's
not her menstrual flow. If it's not her menstrual flow, we can't
use that time to say that she has a regular that's part
of that's her regular period. Okay. אמר רב פפא Rav Papa *Amar
Rav Papa*. אמר רב פפא, Rav Papa אמיסולי שמעתא קמי רב יהודה
מדסקרתא, Amisulei shmaisa kamei Rav Yehuda mi-Diskarta, Disktra, Disktara. Okay, I never
know how to pronounce that word. Anyway, I told this over in
front of רב יהודה from דסקרתא Diskarta and and here was the
question that came up. מקבע לא קבעה, Mikva lo kav'ah, she doesn't
get a fixed וסת vest. during the זבה zavah period. מיחוש מאי
דניחוש לה, Michush mai denichush lah, I asked him, do we have
to be concerned about it, which means what? Let's say a woman
has been bleeding every 20 days. So I get that if next
month she bleeds on day 20, she doesn't have to be concerned
about day 15, because that's one of the הלכות of וסת vest?
קבוע. kavua, But what I want to know is the following, not
whether if it shifts does she still have to be concerned about
it, that definitely not, it's not a וסת vest? קבוע. But does
she have to at least next month stop having sex on day
15? Is it enough of a concern not to say it's a
fixed וסת vest. and that has all the weight of a fixed
וסת, vest but at least that it's a possibility she might bleed
that day and that at least not to have sex during that
time? Okay, is that clear? Meaning right now, let me just put
it in a framework, right, women now most of the time we
assume they have a וסת אינה קבועה, vesset einah kavua, non-fixed וסת,
vest, which means that they have to check, but it also means
if they didn't check, by the way, they can assume they're טהורה,
okay, except for day 30 which I'm not going to talk about,
but generally we assume, so because it's not fixed, if you didn't
check you can assume טהורה. But and if it shifts, you don't
have to be concerned about about what it used to be, because
it's not fixed, but we still say don't have sex on the
day that even if it's not a fixed time on the day
based on last month that you think you might have it. So
that was his question. I get the זבה zavah, period cannot be
a fixed וסת, vest but is it at least a non-fixed וסת,
vestet, a וסת אינה קבועה? vesset einah kavua? Can it at least
be is it at least a time that you have to refrain
from having sex? That was his question. אישתיק, Ishtik, he was silent.
ולא אמר ליה ולא מידי, Velo amar lei velo midi, and he
couldn't respond, he didn't know the answer. So אמר רב פפא, Rav
Papa so okay, so what does this תלמוד Talmud do if he's
not able to get an answer from his רבי? So he says
נחזי אנן, Nechezi anan, let's try to figure it out for ourselves.
Okay, and here's how he tried to figure it out. האי סמוכה
ליום רואה ביום ט"ו, Hai samucha leyom roah beyom tes-vav, going back
to this משנה, a woman normally saw on day 15, which we
now have said was day 22, but let's keep where we go,
ושינתה ליום כ', and she switched to day 20, זו וזו אסורין,
zu vazu asurin, they are both forbidden. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל,
רב יהודה said in the name of שמואל, this is what we
just quoted, לא שנו אלא ט"ו לטבילתה, that this can't be literally
day 15, it has to be 15 from going to the מקוה,
which is day 22, because otherwise it would not be fixed, okay,
ושינתה ליום כ"ז, vashinsah leyom chaf-zayin, and when it says she switches
to day 20, it really means day 27, it's basically add seven
because it's going from the day of טבילה, tevilah, not the day
of becoming a נדה, niddah, right? This is what we've said so
far. The משנה talks about a regular cycle 15, we have to
adjust it so that it fits with the idea that it's not
during the זבה zavah period, and we say 22 and 27 is
what it's talking about. Fine. So how does it get to our
question? So now because then it goes on, it says like this,
דכי הדרי ועבדי כ"ב, De-chi hadrei ve-avdi chaf-bet, what's going to be
the following month? דכי הדרי ועבדי כ"ב, De-chi hadrei ve-avdi chaf-bet, when
you are concerned for day 22, קיימא לה בתוך ימי זיבותה, kaima
lah betoch yemei zivutah, you're in the middle of your זבה zavah
period, ותניא זו וזו אסורין, u-tanya zu vazu asurin, and they're both
forbidden. אלמא דחיישינן, Alma de-chaishinan, you're concerned. Now what does this mean?
I meant to bring a marker, I'll have to try to improvise.
Okay, here's a woman, she sees regularly, it's just the משנה says
15 and 20, but we're going to interpret it as 22 and
27 based on what we said. Okay, fine. So a woman sees
every 20 days. Give me a short, a similar sized marker I
can use for my demonstration period. Okay, so she's been seeing every
20 days, right? 20 days, 20 days, last month she saw 27
days. Comes next month, she has to be חושש choshesh both for
day 20 and day 27. So you would assume that means day
20 and day 27, right? But רב פפא is assuming that since
she's חושש choshesh for day 20, it means that we're imagining her
old cycle is still in place. If her old cycle is still
in place, it's not 20 days out from when she bled here,
it's 20 days out from when she would have bled. So if
we're imagining a concern of the old cycle, 20, 20, 20. So
20 days out from when she would have bled is day 15,
right? This is 27, so it's within the זבה period. So he
says you see we're concerned in the זבה period even though it's
not קבוע, that at least it's enough to refrain from having sex,
assuming we go by what it would have been, not by 20
days from the last time she bled. Okay, so let's read that
inside. Okay. So it says דכי הדרי ועבדי כ"ב, De-chi hadrei ve-avdi
chaf-bet, three lines from the top, דכי הדרי ועבדי כ"ב, De-chi hadrei
ve-avdi chaf-bet, when day 22 arrives, I might have said 20, I
meant 22, day 22 arrives from the last day 22, okay, then
she's in the זבה period, okay, because then it's minus five and
it's day 17, ותניא זו וזו אסורין. u-tanya zu vazu asurin. The
Gemara spells out דקסבר רב פפא, d'kasavar Rav Pappa, Rav Pappa is
assuming עשרים ותרי מעשרים ותרי מנינן, esrim v'tarti me-esrim v'tarti mininan, that
when we are figuring out, again to use the example, day twenty-two
here it's from the virtual day twenty-two, it's not from the last
time she bled, it's when she would have bled. Okay we count
the twenty-two from day twenty-two. נדה ופתחא מעשרים וזיין מנינן לה. Niddah
u-pitzcha me-esrim v'zayin mininan lah. But since he's saying that it's the
זבה period, when it comes to when are we considering her to
be a נדה, niddah when we're considering her to be a זבה,
that is definitely based on the last time she bled, right? I
mean because what makes the problem is he has two different counts
going on here. Right, what makes the counting of the eight to
eighteen is based on the last time she bled. The counting on
when we assume she might be bleeding was based on the last
twenty-two. So that's what it says, to determine the twenty-two according to
him is going from the last twenty-two, what it should have been,
but to determine if she's a נדה niddah, or זבה goes by
when she actually bled. Okay נדה ופתחא מעשרים וזיין מנינן. Niddah u-pitzcha
me-esrim v'zayin mininan. Okay so that's his proof. So there's an obvious
answer to it: don't count from day twenty-two, count from day twenty-seven,
count from the day you actually bled. אמרי ליה רב הונא בריה
דרב יהושע לרב פפא, Amrei lei Rav Huna berei d'Rav Yehoshua l'Rav
Pappa, so Rav Huna the son of Rav Yehoshua said to Rav
Pappa: מימאן? Mimann? Who says that? דאימא עשרים ותרי נמי מעשרים וזיין
מנינן. d'eima esrim v'tarti nami me-esrim v'zayin mininan. We're, yes we're concerned
for day twenty-two but based on the last time she actually bled,
not she should have bled. וכי הדרי יתבי עשרים ותרי v'chi hadrei
yasvei esrim v'tarti and therefore twenty-two days from the last time she
bled, קיימא לה בתוך ימי נדותה, kaima lah b'toch yemei nidatash, during
the נדה niddah period, not the זבה period. Very easy. You count
twenty-two from the last time she bled, there goes your whole proof.
And you know what? להכי נמי מסתברא, l'hachi nami mistavra, it makes
sense to go on based on what actually happened, not what should
have happened. דאילו תימא הכי, d'ilu teima hachi, if you don't say
this, and now I'm very disappointed that Rachel Yehuda isn't here because
here the גמרא makes a, proves something based on not only direct
observation but based on like you know, looking at the animal world
and a certain understanding about the connection between menstruation and like you
know, and birth. So let's take a look. It says like this:
האי תרנגולתא דרמיא יומא וכשיא יומא. Hai tarnegolta d'ramya yoma v'kashya yoma.
Let's say you've got a hen that every other day lays an
egg. When I was young I had an uncle that always used
to ask me these like riddles with hens laying eggs. If a
chicken and a half lays an egg and a half in a
day and a half, anyway I'll tell you the chicken later. Actually,
should I tell you the riddle? If a chicken and a half
lays an egg and a half in a day and a half,
how long does it take six chickens to lay six eggs? No,
a hen, fine whatever. It takes a hen a day and a
half to lay an egg and a half. A hen and a
half, a day and a half to lay an egg and a
half. How long does it take six hens to lay six eggs?
Day and a half. You're multiplying the parallel, day and a half.
Anyway, okay, so anyway here's what he says. You've got a hen
that is laying a day, an egg every other day, okay that's
what this hen is doing. Okay, if she was a cow you'd
call her Betsy, what you would call her I don't know. You've
got a hen, Henrietta, is laying an egg every other day. So
what's going on? דרמיא יומא, d'ramya yoma, she gives an egg one
day, וכשיא יומא, v'kashya yoma, and one day she withholds it, doesn't.
רמיא יומא וכשיא יומא, Ramya yoma v'kashya yoma, lays one egg, doesn't
lay the next day. Every other day she lays an egg. Now
וכשיא תרי יומי, v'kashya trei yomei, one day at one, once she
actually went two days without laying an egg. Okay you got it?
So let's do it even and odd. If it's January, whatever it
is, so she lays on one, not on two. On three yes,
not on four. On five yes, not on six. She lays on
the odd days. In the middle there the month, on days six
and seven she didn't lay. She was supposed to lay on day
seven but she didn't, six and seven she didn't. Now דרמיא חד
יומא, d'ramya chad yoma, now she laid on day eight. When do
you think is the next time she's going to lay? On day
nine or on day ten? What would you say? Ten! We're not
going to say she's going to lay now based on when she
should have laid on day seven so now she's going to lay
on day nine. So he says כי הדרא נקטה, ki hadra nakta,
when she now starts getting back because she was a day suspended,
so now she laid on day eight. So כי הדרא נקטה לטעמיה
נקטה? ki hadra nakta l'tamei nakta? Is it based on what most
recently happened? So she laid now on day eight, the next time
she's going to lay is going to be day ten. או מעיקרא
נקטה? o mi-ka'ara nakta? Or does it go like, oh no, it
used to be odd days so now it's going to keep on
being odd days? על כרחך al korchacha you must admit לטעמיה נקטה,
l'tamei nakta, that it's going to be based on what just happened.
So okay, there was a day she was off, fine, but now
we're back to every other day from what she's doing now. So
now it becomes even days, eight, ten, twelve etc. So therefore the
same here, what she normally seeing on day twenty-two, fine, but now
she saw on day twenty-seven. So the next time she's going to
see even if she's still in her twenty-two cycle is twenty-two from
the last time she bled, from twenty-seven. He's going to go down
swing. אלא הא דאמר ריש לקיש, ela ha de-amar Resh Lakish, she
establishes a וסת בתוך ימי זיבותה. be-tokh yemei zivutah. Now until now
we've been saying that a woman doesn't have a וסת during her
זיבה zivah period. Now we are going to say that ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan disagree with that and actually
say that a woman could have a וסת during her זיבה zivah
period. Okay, let's see what they say. And let's see how this
is relevant. האשה שקבעה לה וסת בתוך ימי זיבותה. ha-ishah she-kavah lah
vest be-tokh yemei zivutah. A woman establishes a וסת during her זיבה
zivah period. ואין האשה קובעת לה וסת בתוך ימי נדותה. ve-ein ha-ishah
kova'at lah vest be-tokh yemei niddutah. But not during her נדה niddah
period. Now what do you mean not during her נדה niddah period?
If she's already a נדה, niddah I mean if it means after
day 18, day 19, that's exactly what a וסת is. Oh. So
we're going to see what it means is not when she could
be a נדה, niddah day 19, it means during the נדה niddah
period itself. Let's say she bleeds and she's a נדה, niddah, and
then let's say, I mean it's obvious if she kept on bleeding
she'd not be another וסת. But let's say actually day two, three,
and four she didn't, and then she bled again on day five.
Can day five count towards becoming a וסת? Okay? Can you have
during the נדה niddah period itself another bleeding, a separate bleeding that
itself has weight towards a וסת? So ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says
no, it's all basically a continuation of what began, and what happens
during the נדה period, the real נדה period, cannot be used towards
a וסת. But he does say the זיבה zivah period can, and
that way it's against what we've been saying until now. But that's
not the relevance of this proof. Okay, he says yes in the
זיבה zivah period as against what we've been saying but not during
the נדה period. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, אשה קובעת לה
וסת בתוך ימי נדותה. ishah kova'at lah vest be-tokh yemei niddutah. And
a woman could establish her וסת during the נדה period. Now what
would be the example? היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? לאתויי,
le-atuyei, it must be she saw כגון דחזא ריש ירחא ובחמישה בירחא,
kegon de-chaza resh yarcha u-ve-chamisha be-yarcha, Rosh Chodesh and day five. ריש
ירחא ובחמישה בירחא, resh yarcha u-ve-chamisha be-yarcha, Rosh Chodesh and day five.
והשתא חזא בחמישה בירחא, ve-hashta chaza be-chamisha be-yarcha, and now she saw
on day five. ובריש ירחא לא חזא, u-ve-resh yarcha lo chaza, and
she did not see on Rosh Chodesh. So he's saying if you've
got one five, one five, five, so therefore if you can use
your נדה bleeding for a וסת, you've now established a pattern of
five because you have three fives, you only have two ones but
three fives, okay, and therefore you've established a pattern of five. So
ובריש ירחא לא חזא, u-ve-resh yarcha lo chaza, you didn't see on
one. So there, and that's the debate. Can you use the five
to make that a וסת or not? Now וקאמר אשה קובעת לה
וסת בתוך ימי נדותה. ve-ka-amar ishah kova'at lah vest be-tokh yemei niddutah.
But why are we, what are we looking at? We're saying the
fives are fives of, assuming you were a נדה, that you bled
on day one. So we're using the five of the third month
without actually having bled, right, because the whole point was you saw
on five and not on one, but we're giving it the same
treatment as the other fives. So you see we use the virtual
what would have been if and we treat that, you know, to
give status to the day. So you see we do go by
virtual and not by actual. Now there's a million ways you can
distinguish those cases, right? I mean, this is not saying when are
we concerned you might bleed again. I mean, actually you say when
are we concerned... anyways, the point is that's his proof. I'll leave
it to you to figure out million reasons why it could be
different, but that's his proof. So you see we use day five
of the third month even though there is no bleeding on day
one. So you see we go by virtual and not just by
actual. So it says אמר ריש ירחא מנינן ליה. amar resh yarcha
maninan lei. So אמר ליה, he said back, לא, no, that's not
the case. It's not the case that day five without a day
one and is based on what would have been. הכי אמר רבי
יוחנן, hachi amar Rabbi Yochanan, this is what Rabbi Yochanan says: כגון
דחזא ריש ירחא וריש ירחא ועשרים וחמישה בירחא וריש ירחא. kegon de-chaza
resh yarcha ve-resh yarcha ve-esrim ve-chamisha be-yarcha ve-resh yarcha. It's not about
using the earlier days of נדה to count, it's about the last
day. Can you use the last day? What's the case? She bled
on day one, on day one, on day minus five and day
one. On day minus five, you know what I mean, it's day
twenty-five of the previous. One, one, minus five, and one. So the
last one you want to use to create three ones and to
have a וסת קבוע. There's a little problem though. The last one
came after the bleeding began five days ago. Can you use that
day one? Right, because that's not standing on its own, it's after
bleeding began earlier. Can you use it to make, you know, to
make three of a kind, like you're playing poker? Okay, so that's
the question. דאמרינן דההיא תוספת היא. de-amrinan de-hahi tosefet hi. If you
can use day one, which is what Rabbi Yochanan says, why can
you use day one? Because given that she's already saw twice on
day one, we'll assume that when she saw on minus five that
was like a precursor, that was for this month was a very
one with a lot of extra blood so she started earlier, but
since day one fits into the pattern, we're willing to bracket the
minus five and use that, that's Rabbi Yochanan's logic. But the relevance
for this debate is it's not based on virtual. Pappos was trying
to say it was a case... רב פפא is trying to say
it was a case of not having one and having five and
we gave five away as if you had seen on day one.
And to prove that we go by when you should have seen,
not by when you actually saw on day one. And the response
back was, no, the case was not when you should have seen,
the case was, the last month you started early, so we have
to discount the day one because you started early. וכי אתא רבין
וכל נחותי ימא, Vechi ata Ravin vechol nachutei yama, and when רבין
Ravin and all those that went down to the ocean, that means
came, they said, came to Bavel, they said אמרוה קמיה דרב הונא
בריה דרב יהושע. Amruha kamei deRav Huna bereih deRav Yehoshua. They said
it like רב הונא the son of רב יהושע, Rav Yehoshua, which
is you count from actual, not from virtual. So that's a very
satisfying resolution based on the reality of the chicken and the hen,
which is a great demonstration. You do not count when you're expecting
your next experience based on when you should have bled last month;
you count from when you actually did bleed. So in the end,
let me just sort of frame what that leaves us with. This
was to answer a question of if you חושש choshesh during ימי
זיבה, but if you can't be a regular וסת, you have to
חושש. choshesh. רב פפא tried to demonstrate it by the way he
read, but that was all assuming you go by virtual, not actual.
That all got rejected. So at the end of the day, we
do not know whether although a woman cannot be קובע וסת, koveia
vestet, we don't know if it's enough of a problem to be
חושש choshesh during ימי זיבה, and then just almost incidentally, we got
introduced to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish at
the end that actually say a woman can be קובע וסת koveia
vestet during ימי זיבה. So at the end of the day, we
have three possibilities for a cycle less than 18 days. Number one,
it can be a וסת קבוע. Number two, it's not a וסת
קבוע, but you might have to be חושש choshesh for it. And
number three, you don't even have to be חושש choshesh for it;
it's nothing. And we really don't have any resolution. If Michael was
here, he would ask מה ההלכה. Ma hahalacha. Charles? I was going
to ask מה יהיה הסוף. Ma yihiyeh hasof. Yes, I think we're
חושש. choshesh. I have to check actually. And I never heard of
this today, making between נידה niddah period and זיבה period. Right, so
because of all conflation of everything anyway, it probably is irrelevant what
we theoretically פוסק pasken about this.